上节课，我们学习了ElGamal公共密钥加密系统
In the last segment, we saw that the
ElGamal public key encryption system is
是在一个有点奇怪的假设下选择的密文安全。今天，我们将
chosen cipher text secure under a somewhat
strange assumption. In this segment, we're
学习ElGamal的变体，方便我们可以选出更好的密码安全文本分析。
gonna look at variants of ElGamal that
have a much better chosen cipher text
在过去的十年里，
security analysis. Now, I should say that
over the past decade, there's been a ton
科学家们在构造上进行了很多研究，也就是用来选择密文安全的公共密钥加密。
of research on constructing, public key
encryptions that are chosen cipher text
事实上，我考虑了很久这里该怎么描述。
secure. I actually debated for some time
on how to best present this here. And
最后，我决定在最近十年中展示一项调查的主要成果。
finally, I decided to kind of show you a
survey of the main results from the last
具体来说，就是他们适用于ElGamal系统时。
decades, specifically as they apply to the
ElGamal system. And then, at the end of
在今天课程的结尾，我会推荐给大家一些论文，大家可以进行更深层次的学习。
the module, I suggest a number of papers
that you can look at for further reading.
那么我们今天的课程从回忆ElGamal加密系统的工作过程开始。
So let me start by reminding you how the
ElGamal encryption system works. I'm sure
我确定到现在为止你们还都记得ElGamal是如何工作的，保险起见，我帮助大家回忆
by now you all remember how ElGamal works,
but just to be safe, let me remind you
ElGamal中的密钥生成挑选一个随机发生器，还有一个从ZN中产生的随机指数。
that key generation in ElGamal picks a
random generator, a random exponent from ZN
并且公共密钥是一个简单的发生器，并且元素是g到a，
and then the public key is simply the
generator and this element g to the a,
即私密密钥是基为g的离散对数h。由这些可以计算出A。
whereas the secret key is simply the
discrete log of h base g. This value A.
现在我们加密的方式是在ZN中挑选随机指数B。我们计算
Now the way we encrypt is we pick a random
exponent B from ZN. We compute the hash of
G到B和H到B的哈希函数。接下来，H到B是Diffie Hellman秘密，G到AB。
G to the B and H to the B. And I'm gonna
remind you that H to the B is the Diffie
这样，我们实际上是运用一个对称加密系统
Hellman secret, G to the AB. And then we
actually encrypt a message using a
和一个从哈希函数中派生出的密钥K加密了一条信息。
symmetric encryption system with the key K
that's derived from the hash function. And
最终，输出密文是G到B，也就是对称密文。
finally, the output cipher text is G to
the B, and the symmetric cipher text. The
我们解密的方法也就是我们之前学过的，将U哈希并且Diffie Hellman 秘密，
way we decrypt is you know, as we've seen
before basically, by hashing U and the
将对称系统进行解密，并且输出信息M。
Diffie Hellman secrets, decrypting the
symmetric system, and outputting the
上节课的最后我们讲到ElGamal用来选择密文安全，
message M. Now in the last segment we said
that ElGamal is chosen ciphertext secure under
基于这个可爱的Diffie Hellman交互式假设。那么这里的这个假设是什么呢。
this funny Interactive Diffie-Hellman
assumption. I am not gonna remind you what
这里我还想提到，这个定理提出了两个很自然的问题。
the assumption is here but I'll also say
that this theorem kind of raises two very
第一个问题是，我们能否只基于标准的计算Diffie Hellman假设
natural questions. The first question is
can we prove CCA security of
证明ElGamal下CCA的安全性，
ElGamal just based on the standard
Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption,
即G到A，G到B，你不能计算G到AB。
namely the G to the A, G to the B, you
can't compute G to the AB. Can we prove
我们能不能仅仅基于此证明已选择的密文安全性呢？答案是有两种方式
chosen-ciphertext security just based on
that? And the truth's that there are two
来做到。第一个选择是运用一个计算性DH假设用起来比较困难的组。
ways to do it. The first option is to use
a group where the computational Diffie
但是可证明它和交互式DH假设是相当的。
Hellman assumption is hard. But is
provably equivalent to the Interactive
这说明了事实上构造这样的组不是很困难。
Diffie Hellman assumption. And it turns
out it's actually not that hard to
这些组我们称为双线性组。
construct such groups. These groups are
called bilinear groups. And in such
在这些组里，我们知道ElGamal系统用来选择密文安全，
groups, we know that the ElGamal system is
chosen cipher text secure, strictly based
是严格基于计算性DH假设的，至少也是在随机的订购模型中。
under the Computational Diffie Hellman
assumption, at least in the random oracle
这些双线性组事实上是从非常特殊的椭圆曲线中构造的。
model. I'll tell you that these bi-linear
groups are actually constructed from very
所以这几个代数结构帮助我们证明IDH和CDH的等价性。
special elliptic curves. So there's a bit
more algebraic structure that enables us
但是，通常情况下，
to prove this equivalence of IDH and CDH.
But in general, who knows, maybe you don't
我们并不想运用椭圆曲线组，可能我们由于某些原因更想用ZP star.
want to use elliptic curve groups, maybe
you want to use ZP star for some reason.
因此这是一个自然提出来的问题。我们能不能改变ElGamal系统使得
So it's a pretty natural question to ask.
Can we change the ElGamal system such that
ElGamal下的选择密文安全性现在可以被证明，而且是直接基于CDH下，对于CDH使用困难时的组？
chosen ciphertext security of ElGamal now can be proven, directly based on CDH, for any group
假设这个组有一些附加的结构，
where CDH is hard? [Now with that ??] assuming
any additional structure about the group,
那么答案就是可以。有一种精巧的构造叫做twin ElGamal.
And it turns out the answer is yes. And
there's kind of an elegant construction
接下来我们介绍twin ElGamal是如何工作的 。
called twin ElGamal, so let me show you
how twin ElGamal works. It's a very simple
这是个很简单的ElGamal的变体。再一次，在密钥生成模式中，
variation of ElGamal that does the
following. Again, in key generation, we
我们选择一个随机的生成器。但是这一次，我们将选择两个指数，A1和A2来作为
choose a random generator. But this time,
we're gonna choose two exponents, A1 and
私密密钥。因此私密密钥也就有了两个指数，分别是A1和A2。
A2 as the secret key. So the secret key is
gonna consist of these two exponents, A1
公共密钥是由我们的生成器构成的。
and A2. You know the public key of course
is gonna consist of our generator. And
接下来我们要释放G到A1和G到A2.所以记住通常的ElGamal下，
then we're gonna release G to the A1 and G
to the A2. So remember that in regular
公共密钥就是简单的从G到A。我们有两个指数，
ElGamal what the public key is simply g
to the A and that's it. Here we have two
A1和A2 ，因此我们释放G到A1和G到A2。
exponents A1 and A2 and therefore we, we
release both G to the A1 and G to the A2.
现在我们加密的方式，你会注意到公共密钥在这里是一个比常规ElGamal长的元素。
Now the way we encrypt, you'll notice the
public key here is one element longer than
我们用这个公共密钥加密的方式事实上和常规ElGamal十分相似。
regular ElGamal. The way we encrypt using
this public key is actually very similar
我们选择一个随机的B，现在我们要做的哈希事实上不是
to regular ElGamal. We choose a random B,
and now what we'll hash is actually not
从G到B，从H1到B，事实上是从G到B，从H1到B，从H2到B。
just G to the B and H1 to the B, but,
in fact, G to the B, H1 to the B, and H2
我们事实上对三个而不是两个元素进行了哈希变换，
to the B. Okay so we basically hashing
three elements instead of two elements and
我们运用派生的对称加密密钥加密了信息，
then we basically encrypt the message
using the derived symmetric encryption key
并且输出G到B和C作为最终密文。那么我们如何解密呢？
and as usual we output g to the b and c as our
final ciphertext. How do we decrypt?
现在私密密钥由两个指数组成，A1和A2。
Well, so now the secret key consists of
these two exponents, A1 and A2. And the
密文包括U和对称密文C。这里我们提出一个问题，
cipher text consists of U, and the
symmetric cipher text C. So let me ask you
看看大家是否能找出仅仅运用给出的私密密钥和计算值U来
a puzzle, and see if you can figure out
how to derive the symmetric encryption key
派生出对称加密密钥K的方法。这是个很有趣的问题，
K, just given the secret key and the value
U. So it's kind of a cute puzzle and I
我希望大家都能解开它。解决方法是
hope everybody worked out, the solution
which is basically what we can do is we
我们用U乘以A1的幂，这就是G到B，A1，和U到A2，G到B A2。
can take U to the power of A1, and that is
basically G to the B A1 And U to the A2
我们会得到完全相同的值，就像H1到B和H2到B。
which is G to the B A2. And that basically
gives us exactly the same values, as H1 to
这种方式的解密我们得到了相同的对称密钥，
the B and H2 to the B. So this way the
decryptor arrives at the same symmetric
正如加密中做到的。接着我们运用对称系统解密密文
key that the encryptor did. Then he decrypts
the ciphertext using the symmetric system
并最终输出信息M。因此你会发现这是一个对于常规ElGamal非常简单的改进。
and finally outputs the message M. So you
notice this is a very simple modification
我们所做的只是在公共密钥中多选了一个元素。
to regular ElGamal. All we do is we stick
one more element to the public key. When
当我们做哈希变换时，多对一个元素进行，也就是不只两个元素，
we do the hashing, we hash one more
element, as opposed to just two elements.
我们对三个元素进行了哈希变换。相似的，我们进行解密，其他的都没改变。
We hash three elements. And similarly, we
do doing decryption, and nothing else
密文长度也和之前相同。
changes. The cipher text is the same
length as before, and that's it, Now the
惊异的是这样简单的修改就能让我们证明
amazing thing is that this simple
modification allows us to now prove chosen
直接选择密文安全，基于标准计算性Diffie-Hellman假设
cipher text security directly based on
standard Computational Diffie-Hellman
仍假设一个对称加密系统
assumption, okay? Still we're going to
need to assume that we have a symmetric
提供我们认证加密以及散列函数
encryption system that provides us
authenticated encryption and that the hash
这里用的是理想的散列函数，我们称为随机的Oracle数据库
function that we're using is an ideal hash
function in what we call a random oracle
但是考虑到要严格证明选择密文安全
But nevertheless given that, we can
prove chosen cipher text security strictly
基于一个计算Diffie-Hellman的假设。现在的成本是什么？
based on a Computational Diffie-Hellman
assumption. So now what's the cost of this?
如果你去思考，在加密与加密之间，加密必须
Of course, if you think about this, during
encryption and decryption, encryption has
多做一个求幂运算，那么解密也得多做求幂运算
to do one more exponentiation, and the
decryption has to do one more
现在加密机做三次求幂运算
exponentiation. So the encryptor now does
three exponentiations instead of two, and
而解密机做两次求幂运算
the decryptor does two exponentiations
instead of one. So the question is now,
现在变成了哲学问题。这些额外的努力都值得吗？
now it's a philosophical question. Is this
extra effort worth it? So you do more work
在加密和解密多做了工作。公开密钥变得更大
during encryption and decryption. And your
public key is a little bit bigger, but
但这并没关系。在加密和解密做的工作是更有意义的
that doesn't really matter. The work
during encryption and decryption is more
结果得到选择密文安全性基于一种
significant. And as a result you get
chosen ciphertext security based on kind
更为自然的假设，也就是计算Diffie-Hellman与
of a more natural assumption, namely
Computational Diffie-Hellman as opposed to
这些外形奇特的Diffie-Hellman假设。但是值得吗？
these odd-looking Interactive
Diffie-Hellman assumption. But is it worth
问题是这些群CDH持有而IDH并不持有
it? Kind of the question is are there
groups where CDH holds but IDH does not
如果存在这些群，那么当然值得这么做
hold? If there were such groups, then it
would definitely be worth it, because
因为这些群，这两个性能就会安全，但常规的性能
those groups, the twin ElGamal would be
secure, but the regular ElGamal would not
就不再有CCA安全了。不幸的是我们并不清楚是否存在这样的群
be CCA secure. But unfortunately we don't
know if there is any such group and in
存在CDH与IDH同时持有的群当然是可能的
fact as far as we know, it's certainly
possible that any group where CDH holds,
但是却并不知道额外的花费值不值得
IDH also holds. So the answer is, really,
we don't know whether the extra cost is
不过这是个好玩的结果，说明如果想要
worth it or not but then nevertheless it's
a cute result that shows that if you want
直接从CDH得到选择密文安全
to achieve chosen ciphertext
security directly from CDH, you could do
你可以不通过对性能系统做过多的改变来完成。接下来的问题是
it without too many changes to the ElGamal
system. The next question is whether we
我们能否摆脱这种假设，即哈希函数为理想的散列函数
can get rid of this assumption that the
hash function is an ideal hash function
主要为一个随机Oracle数据库。这会是一个巨大的话题
mainly that it's a random oracle. And this
is actually a huge topic. There's a lot of
在如何建立高效的公共密钥加密系统上有很多工作需要完成
work in this area on how to build
efficient public key encryption systems
这里的选择密文安全是不用随机Oracle函数的
that are chosen ciphertext secure without
random oracles. This is a very active area
在过去十年或更长的时间里这是一个非常活跃的研究领域
of research as I said in the past decade
and even longer. And I'll mention that as
它适用于性能为两个群的结构
it applies to ElGamal, they are basically,
again two families of constructions. The
第一个结构运用了这些特殊的群称作双线性组
first construction's a construction that
uses these special groups called these
原来的双线性组结构
bilinear groups that I just mentioned
before. It turns out the extra structure
允许我们建立非常有效的选择密文安全系统
of these bilinear groups allows us to
build very efficient chosen ciphertext
而并未使用随机Oracle数据库，而在结束时的模块
secure systems without referring to random
oracles and as I said at the end of the
我指出了大量的论文来解释做法。这是一个很有意思的结构
module, I point to a number of papers that
explain how to do that. This is quite an
但这需要几个小时来解释它是如何工作的
interesting construction. But it will take
me several hours to kind of explain how it
其他替代方法实际上使用一个更强的决定Diffie-Hellman假设群
works. The other alternative is actually
to use groups where a stronger assumption
再次，我并不证明这个假设
called the Decision Diffie-Hellman assumption
holds. Again, I am not gonna define this
我只告诉你这个假设实际上有ZP星号标记的子群
assumption here. I'll just tell you that
this assumption actually holds in
特别是如果我们看ZP星号标记主要子群的阶
subgroups of ZP star, in particular if we
look at the prime order of a subgroup of
选择Diffie-Hellman假设似乎在这些群中持有
ZP star. The Decision Diffie-Hellman
assumption seems to hold in those groups
在这些群中我们可以建立一个变种的性能称作
and then in those groups we can actually
build a variant of ElGamal, called the
克莱默苏泊系统，为选择密文安全和
Cramer Shoup system that is chosen
ciphertext secure and the Decision
没有随机Oracle数据库的选择Diffie-Hellman假设
Diffie-Hellman assumption without random
oracles. Again, this is a beautiful,
这是一个很好的结果但是需要几个小时来解释，所以我也不在这展示
beautiful result but again it would take a
couple of hours to explain and so I'm not
这可能是其中一件事我留下来
gonna do that here. This is probably one
of these things that I gonna leave to
并不是先进的主题或做一个先进的课题，所以我们在之后在解决
either the advanced topics or to do an
advanced course so that we'll do it at a
但我还是提供一篇论文在结束时的模块以防
later time. But again I points to a paper
at the end of the module just in case you
你想了解更多相关内容。这里的论文目录提供了更多的阅读材料
want to read more about this. So here is a
list of papers that provides more reading
如果你想读Diffie Hellman假设
material. So if you wanna read about
Diffie Hellman assumptions, I guess I
我在早前写过一篇相关论文谈过各种关于Diffie Hellman的相关假设
wrote a paper about this a long time ago,
that talks about various assumptions
特别是对选择Diffie Hellman假设的研究
related to, to Diffie Hellman. And in
particular, studies the Decision Diffie
如果你想学习如何建立选择密文安全系统
Hellman assumption. And if you wanna learn
about how to build chosen ciphertext
通过选择Diffie-Hellman假设或类似的假设
secure system from Decision Diffie-Hellman
and assumptions like it. There's a very
Kramer和Shoup在2002年写的论文就说明了如何解决
cute paper by Kramer and Shoup back
from 2002 that shows how to do it. This is
这篇非常强烈推荐去看看。如果你想学习如何
again a very highly recommended paper. If
you want to learn how to build chosen
通过双线性组建立选择密文安全，那么推荐你读的论文
ciphertext security from these
bilinear groups, then the paper to read is
就是引用在这里的，使用了一个叫做Identity Based Encryption的通用机制
the one, cited here, which actually uses a
general mechanism called Identity Based
非常惊喜的是它给我们的选择密文安全几乎是免费的
Encryption which very surprisingly it
turns out to actually gives us chosen
一旦我们建立身份加密
ciphertext security almost for free.
So, once we build identity-based
选择密文安全就立即下降。这覆盖在我的这篇论文中
encryption chosen ciphertext security falls
immediately. And that's covered in this
双Diffie-Hellman结构在引用的论文中被证明
paper that I, that I describe her. The
Twin Diffie-Hellman construction and its
最后，如果你想看最近的一篇论文
proof is described in this paper that I
reference here And finally, if you kind of
它给了一个非常通用的框架
want to see a very recent paper. That
gives a very general framework for
来建立选择密文安全系统，使用了所谓可推断出的散列证明
building, chosen ciphertext secure systems, using
what's called extractable hash proofs that
是Hoeteck Wee写的一篇论文，是最近才发表的
is again a nice paper by Hoeteck Wee, that
was just recently published. I definitely
我希望你们都能完整地阅读这一篇，有很多不错的想法在里面
recommend reading it all, all have
very, very elegant ideas in them. I wish I
我希望我可以在基础课上涵盖所有内容，但是我不得不
could cover all of them in the basic
course but I'm gonna have to leave some of
留出更多时间给更先进的课程或更课题在结课前
these to the more advanced course or
perhaps the more advanced topics at the
这节课到这，下节课我将
end of this course. Okay, so I'll stop
here and in the next segment I'm gonna tie
将性能和RSA加密结合，让你了解
ElGamal and RSA encryption
together so that you see how the two kind
如何让这两者遵循更一般的原则
of follow from a more general principle.